<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continued iournall of all the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham his Grace, in the Isle of Ree, since the last of August</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111536</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846853</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846853</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11847</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14424)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11847)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1159:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continued iournall of all the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham his Grace, in the Isle of Ree, since the last of August</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 9, [3] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[ugustine] M[athewes] for Thomas Walkley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Eagle and Childe in Britaines-Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: September 18.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf contain woodcuts of ships.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckingham, George Villiers, --  Duke of, 1592-1628.</term>
               <term>Ré Expedition, 1627 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11847:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 92 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:11847:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 92 -->
            <p>A Continued <hi>September</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> IOVRNALL OF ALL THE PROCEEDING<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Duke of BVCKINGHAM his Grace, in the Iſle of Ree, ſince the laſt of Auguſt.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>TEMPORE PATET OCCVLTA VERITAS</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Walkley,</hi> and are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Eagle</hi> and <hi>Childe</hi> in <hi>Britaines-Burſſe.</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11847:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 93 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11847:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 93 -->
            <head>THE IOVRNALL CONTINVED TO <hi>THIS DAY. Receiued the</hi> 18. <hi>of September.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as report, that is ſeldome conſtant, is very different concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Subiect which in time and place is ſo nere, I meane the Siedge of Saint <hi>Martins</hi> Cittadell, vnder the conduct of his Illuſtrious Excellency, the Duke of BVCKINGHAN. I thought it would bee an acceptable relation, to diſcouer, by way of a demonſtratiue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, the ſtate both of the Leaguer and Fort, according to that Intelligence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11847:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 94 -->
which I haue receiued from a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of worth and qualitie.</p>
            <p>You muſt therefore vnderſtand, that the Engliſh Army now lying before the Cittadell, hauing intrenched themſelues ſtrongly, labour continually to drawe their approaches and batteries neerer, and although the earth is ill to worke in (as being altogether Rocky or Sandy) yet our men being encouraged with the preſence of their Generall, haue at length (though not without ſweet and danger) raiſed a new Reintrenchment and Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</p>
            <p>Beſides, our Souldiers who ſupplie the place of Pioners, haue ſuncke a Mine of the Enemies, nere the Foundation of the vtmoſt Counterſcarffe, by the blowing vp whereof, they hope to open a breach but they doe not ſpring this Mine as yet, expecting thoſe Reinforcements, which are to come from <hi>England,</hi> vpon whoſe arriuall, we doubt not, but that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie (who is already much diſtreſſed for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11847:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 94 -->
want of neceſſary accomodations) will ſurrender vp the Fort without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inforcement.</p>
            <p>Our approaches are brought ſo neere vnto the Enemies, that wee are able to throw a Coite from our works to theirs, and the like may they doe, from theirs to ours. But if all other courſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts ſhould faile, we are aſſured by all probable aduertiſements, and conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, that the beſiedged cannot hold out long, they being ſo much neceſsita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for want of victualls, as hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued no reliefe from the Continent, neuer ſince the beginning of the Siedge.</p>
            <p>Our men haue them ſo continuall in the eye, that they dare not looke ouer their workes for feare of our Canon, and Musket ſhot.</p>
            <p>Our Souldiers deliuer braue teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of reſolution and valour, ſo that by the very confeſsion of the Enemie, they are reputed as daring men as any are in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:11847:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 95 -->To which actions of Honour, they are not ſo much encouraged by the precept of Diſcipline, as by the Example of their Generall, who cheeriſheth the valient, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth the wauering, and puniſheth (though mildely) the ſlothfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actiue Souldier; and beſides his perſonall night-watches, and walking of the firſt round, hee doth perſonally preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the Face of all neceſſary dangers.</p>
            <p>Which motiues of preſident doe ſo ſtrongly confirme the vertue of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> that like men lauiſh of their liues, they aduenture themſelues to all perrills, and hazards.</p>
            <p>So that if they were not reſtrained by the curbe of Military obedience, they could hardly be kept backe from aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Fort without command.</p>
            <p>Yet there are ſome maleuolent ſpirits who are luke-warme in affection, either to the Duke, or to the cauſe, haue main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with an opinionatiue obſtinacy, that the taking of the Fort is not ſeazable,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11847:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 95 -->
yet our men who are there ingaged, (amongſt whom there are diuers ſolid iudgements) doe as confidently beleeue, as if they had diſplayed their Enſignes vpon the walles thereof already, that they ſhall bee maſters of it vpon the firſt arriuall of the next ſupplies from <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fort (notwithſtanding rumour hath blazed the contrary) is very ill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of Victualls and other neceſſaries, for beſides the want of water and fuell, (the want whereof is the interdiction of Mankinde) they are very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed for want of Bread, Fleſh and other neceſſaries; ſince the cutting off their Conducts, and poyſoning of their Well, they haue no other freſh water, but what they make ſhift to receiue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sheets hung vp in the ayre for that purpoſe of receiuing that vncertaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Heauens, which was a great refreſhment vnto the Enemie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11847:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 96 -->Their Bread is allotted and allowed vnto the Souldiers that are in the Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell by ſmall proportions, for each one of them hath leſſe then halfe a pound a day for his nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>Alſo the like is done to their Water, for which they may thanke God that this Autumnall wett weather fell out ſo luckily.</p>
            <p>All their Horſes (which being of the choiſeſt breede of <hi>France,</hi> were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the Saddle, &amp; not for the Palate) are either killed for want of water, or eaten for the ſatisfying of the hungry Souldiers: ſo that they haue not ſo much as one Horſe left aliue, nor any freſh Victualls to releeue themſelues withall.</p>
            <p>They are onelie cheriſhed with windie hopes of ſuccour from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, which thoſe of <hi>Angoliſme</hi> and <hi>Poictowe</hi> promiſe, but this is like to bee meere winde without ſucceſſe, without effect: for his <hi>Excellency</hi> knowing that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11847:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 96 -->
preuention is the ſpirit of pollicie and the life of offence and defence, hath vſed ſuch prouiſionall courſes of interception, that in humane reaſon it is not to bee ſuccou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French King</hi> hath beene moſt deſperatly ſicke at <hi>Villeroy</hi> and as we here he is not yet perfectly recouered.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Count of Soiſſons</hi> (who fled the laſt yeare into <hi>Sauoy,</hi> being diſcontented with the gouernement of <hi>France</hi>) is making newe leuies againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and as it is reported, diuers other <hi>Princes</hi> ſtand vpon theire guards and proper defence.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rochellers</hi> receiue our ſicke men willingly, and entertaine our Souldiers who come to the Towne, with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of loue and courteſie.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the care of his <hi>Excellencie:</hi> ſome of our men (but thoſe not many) haue fallen into fluxes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes, by eating of Grapes and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11847:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 97 -->
drinking of Wine, which agrees not with Engliſh bodies as well as beere, that drinke being moſt agreeing with nature, which is firſt vſed from our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie, Thoſe that are ſicke and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded are carefully looked vnto by Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians Chirurgions, and if they want freſh meate his <hi>Excellencies</hi> care is ſuch, that he cauſeth preſent prouiſion to bee made for them, ſo that very fewe of them dye, by meanes of theſe neceſſary and carefull helpes.</p>
            <p>His Excellence hath giuen a ſtrict and ſpeciall charge to all the Phyſitians and Chyrurgians to ſee their ſtore well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of all neceſſary medicinalls for a winter Leaguer.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe his Excellence hath cauſed a Proclamation to bee publiſhed of late, that no man ſhould ſtirre out of his quarters vpon paine of a ſeuere penalty, for feare that the Enemie ſhould make any deſperate attempt or ſally which as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11847:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 97 -->
yet they neuer attempted.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French King</hi> hath ſent diuerſe companies of Foote, and troopes of Horſe into the Iland of <hi>Oleron,</hi> but by GODS aſſiſtance and the complying of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, we ſhall keepe them from ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring the beſeeged.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the Journall.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
